Mss.B.St15
American Philosophical Society
Jacob Stauffer Papers, 1844-1879
Mss.B.St15
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet Ca. 235 items
These letters concern various scientific subjects, such as fishes, insects, snakes, mice, fossils, and mosses. Other subjects include learned institutions, notably the Smithsonian Institution and the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, and men of science. Correspondents include S. S. Haldeman, Walter J. Hoffman, Spencer F. Baird, Edward D. Cope, and Leo Lesquereux.
Ca. 235 items.
Stauffer, Jacob,b. 1808.
Box 1
General note
Film 1321
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of 238 items dated between 1844 and 1879. While some of the letters refer to botanical matters, much of the material relates to Stauffer’s interest in entomology. Stauffer apparently assumed his entomological studies around 1855, as is suggested by encouraging letters from Spencer Fullerton Baird (4 June 1855) and Samuel Stehman Haldeman (22 June 1855). Even though Stauffer was entirely self-taught, he eventually enjoyed the respect of several prominent naturalists who did not hesitate to consult him with questions about entomological and related subjects. Futhermore, many items in the collection shed light on Stauffer’s efforts to gain employment and get his work published. Finally, a few letters deal with religious matters.
The list of Stauffer’s correspondents includes the names of distinguished naturalists, including Haldeman, Le Conte, and Drinker. The letters from Edward Cope Drinker, who served for a time as secretary of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, for example, relate information about various animals, including especially fishes. He often asks Stauffer for clarification on questions that puzzled him, including the identity of “three strangers” that he found in his “booty” of specimens he brought home from a collecting expedition (22 June 1866). On one occasion, Stauffer evidently asked Drinker to examine an old museum specimen of a snake that was said to have a frog inside. Drinker opened the snake, found the frog – and “smelled humbug” (11 March 1867). Marshall J. Udderzook, the owner of the snake, subsequently questioned Drinker’s conclusion that the frog in the snake constituted an act of deception. He wrote to Stauffer that he had “no desire to swindle humbug cheat or to impose upon any man or set of men either of science or any other class” (26 March 1867).
Other correspondents include J. S. Houghton, who also frequently sent specimens of insects. Josiah Hoopes of the Cherry Hill Nurseries occasionally asked Stauffer for help in identifying insects and other animals he found in his plants, including a “crowd of worms” that had destroyed a number of evergreens (24 December 1866), and Charles Riley, editor of The American Entomologist, requested Stauffer to send specimens of certain galls to confirm whether they matched a forthcoming set of illustrations (Nov.,Dec. 1868). The Portland Society of Natural History asked Stauffer for specimen and “to open correspondence” with him “with a view to exchanges in [his] own specialty” (5 April 1869). Joseph Henry of the Smithsonian Institution also corresponded with Stauffer. In 1853, for example, the two naturalists exchanged information about “the parasitical character of our comandra” (5 September 1853), and thirteen years later Henry informs Stauffer that the Smithsonian will support his application to receive some shells from the collection of the Smithsonian Institution (14 March 1866).
The material reflects Stauffer’s connection to various groups of naturalists, including the Lancaster City and County Horticultural Society, the Entomological Society of Philadelphia, and the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. Stauffer was also active in the Linnaean Society of Lancaster, which had been founded by Simon Snyder Rathvon, a friend and frequent correspondent of Stauffer. Some of the material in the collection dates to the 1860s, when Stauffer served as the Society’s secretary. That the Society was smaller than its members hoped for is suggested by a note from Rathvon. Rathvon suggests that the Society send out an announcement to the members to be punctual for a meeting with Mr. Gilbert who, Rathvon fears, “expects the Linnaean is a ‘bigger thing’ than it really is (27 January 1874).
Items that shed light on Stauffer’s publications in newspapers and magazines include a letter from S. S. Loss, editor of the The Farm and Fireside, that acknowledges Stauffer’s valuable contribution to the magazine (25 February 1867). The letter from Moore, editor of Moore’s Rural New-Yorker, invites Stauffer to write an illustrated column (30 June 1870). Subsequent letters by Moore apologize for not publishing certain articles in a timely manner (see, for example, 6 December 1871). Josiah Hoopes of the Pennsylvania Fruit Growers’ Society asked Stauffer for a “plain, practical” article for its report (10 February 1872), and John Jay Smith wrote a number of letters relating to Stauffer’s contributions to The Horticulturist. Stauffer seemed to have been particularly adept in writing for a broad audience. However, a note by Elbert S. Carman suggests that some of the articles he submitted to The Rural New-Yorker “are almost too scientific” (undated). Stauffer’s illustrations were particularly well received, as a letter by S. S. Rathvon suggests. “How I wish I had your talent and tact for drawing,” Rathvon writes, “your figures are truthful and as recognizable as many engravings” (25 June 1855). Similarly, Baird urged Stauffer to make “an elaborate portfolio of highly finished drawings illustrating insects and their transformations. They will be very useful one day” (28 January 1857). Thomas Conrad Porter also expressed confidence that Stauffer had the talent to produce excellent work (2 November 1857).
Some material documents Stauffer’s efforts to secure employment in the field of natural sciences. The letters not only make clear that Stauffer turned to several of his acquaintances for assistance in finding employment, but they also show that they were generally unable to help him. For example, Joseph Henry writes about the lack of employment opportunities at the Smithsonian (11 July 1853), and Spencer Fullerton Baird is pessimistic about securing for Stauffer “a position in an expedition or otherwise” (15 February 1855). Similarly, John Jay Smith is “very unable to give much advice,” but recommends that Stauffer pursue employment by the state (9 January 1858). Stauffer apparently followed the suggestion, as is indicated by a letter from John Gottlieb Morris (27 January 1858).
Stauffer, who at times worked as a physician, druggist and lawyer, had trouble earning an income with his scientific pursuits, including his research, articles and illustrations. Of particular interest in this context is an item somewhat erroneously labeled “autobiographical sketch.” The undated document, which was written by Stauffer when he resided in Mount Joy, offers ruminations about his life, including the fact that he has not been able to generate a decent income, in part because of his conscience. He writes, for example, that he is a doctor and druggist in want of money but “for the life of me cannot bring myself to invent Quack Medicines—bleed and purge folks, or tinker with their health, to get their money.” Stauffer goes on to lament that “the honest simple heart” had not earned him any money, and while the ones “who had but one ‘idea’ and that for ‘making money’” are living well, he has “not so much as a wheel barrow or habitation of [his] own.” The essay concludes with the hope that Stauffer find “an honest Man of Capital” who would help him pay for the publication of his book.
Finally, Stauffer was an active member of the Presbyterian church. Letters related to religious matter include the note from Albert Barnes (29 September 1851), and a letter by Rathvon that speculates about “the reason why Moses prohibited the eating of swines flesh” (16 March 1862).
Early American History Note
The Jacob Stauffer Collection contains correspondence about science and scientific institutions in the United States. Only one letter dates to before the 1850s (1844).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased and accessioned, 1955 (1955 1796ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Jacob Stauffer (1808–1880) was a lawyer, naturalist, printer, lithographer, and photographer. Stauffer’s scientific investigations dealt with various subjects, including insects, snakes, mice, fossils, and mosses; however, his main interests were entomology and the classification of fish. His notebooks were filled with his descriptions and illustrations, some of which he published as woodcuts or lithographs himself. He met and corresponded with many eminent naturalists of his day.
Jacob Stauffer was born in 1808 in Manheim, Lancaster County, Pennsylvania, the son of the clockmaker Samuel C. Stauffer and his wife Hannah Wright Stauffer. The boy received a “common school education” and from a young age worked at his father’s store in town. Stauffer displayed a remarkable talent for drawing and painting; however, his father refused to support his son’s career in art. Instead, a retired West Pointer, who was boarding with his family for a time, inspired young Jacob to pursue military training. Stauffer was later appointed adjutant of the Eighteenth Regiment of the Pennsylvania Militia (1825), and eventually became its first major and finally colonel.
Around 1820, Stauffer moved to Philadelphia, where he became acquainted with Thomas Sully (1783-1872, APS 1835), Henry Inman (1801-1846) and other artists and engravers. He took classes in drawing and oil painting while supporting himself with a clerkship in the counting house of S. Eckstein, and later in the recording office of Philadelphia. In 1830 he returned to Manheim to open a store and operate a printing press. He is believed to have printed the town’s first, but short-lived, newspaper. His interest in natural history eventually compelled Stauffer to sell off his general merchandise and become an apothecary.
Stauffer remained in Manheim for about eight years, until he moved to Richland, now part of Mount Joy. To this town he introduced the first printing press, a lithographic press and daguerreotypy, which had only recently been invented. He was a member of the council and school board as well as the First Presbyterian Church and Sunday school. His various avocations did not prevent him from devoting much of his time to the study of natural history. He collected specimens and made detailed notes and drawings on his rambles through the area around Mount Joy. His son David McNeely Stauffer wrote that “among my earliest recollections are the happy Saturdays spent in long walks through the countryside with my father, searching for rare plants and insects.”
Stauffer’s contributions to natural science include important observations on the parasitism of certain native Scrophulariaceae, and of the Comandra umbellate, which Asa Gray (1810-1888, APS 1848) published in Silliman’s Journal in 1853. Stauffer’s talent as an artist is evident in the large manuscript books he filled with his descriptions and colored drawings. In 1853 he published at Gray’s urging a pamphlet that was produced entirely by his own hand: he described his “investigations,” drew the illustrations, printed the lithographs, and stitched the pages. The little book included descriptions of some of the plants he had discovered on his walks. After 1854 Stauffer also contributed drawings and essays on botany to his son’s newspaper, the Mount Joy Herald.
Stauffer’s scientific accomplishments also included the discovery of several new species of fishes, including the singular blind catfish. Stauffer, who was entirely self-taught, corresponded about various scientific topics with many prominent naturalists of his day, including Asa Gray, Joseph Henry (1797-1878, APS 1835), Samuel Haldeman (1812-1880, APS 1844), Edward D. Cope (1840-1897, APS 1866) and John L. Le Conte (1825-1883, APS 1853), all of whom recognized the significant scientific value of Stauffer’s work. As the biographer Alexander Harris noted in 1872, “if a strange plant or insect is found and a name wanted for it, you are usually advised to ‘go to Stauffer, he can tell you.’” However, his accomplishments have remained largely obscure due to the fact that even though he contributed many essays and drawings to newspapers and journals, his illustrated manuscript books were never published. Harris explained that Stauffer resisted publication of his notebooks because he had in the books of others “found nothing new and no improvement on works previously written in the same subject.” He evidently did not want to risk producing such a book himself.
In the panic of 1858 Stauffer lost his property after he had endorsed a note for a presumably wealthy friend. As a result he moved to Lancaster, where his son Henry Francis had established himself as a newspaper editor. Stauffer unsuccessfully petitioned the state legislature to support him as a state entomologist for a period of three years. His friend Emanuel C. Reigart (1796-1869) then helped him to secure the job as librarian at the Lancaster Athenaeum, which Reigart had founded. He also received permission to conduct a patent consulting business on the premises of the library and museum. In his capacity as a patent solicitor Stauffer completed many drawings of machinery and patented articles.
In 1862 Stauffer belonged to a group of several local naturalists, including Simon Snyder Rathvon (1812-1891), who founded the Linnaean Society of Lancaster. Stauffer served as the society’s secretary. He also belonged to the Lancaster City and County Horticultural Society, the Entomological Society of Philadelphia, and he was elected a corresponding member of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia in 1866. Stauffer was also for many years a leading elder in the Lancaster Presbyterian Church.
Stauffer died in Lancaster in 1880. He remained his entire life a man of modest circumstances. Nevertheless, he never deprived himself from acquiring a book or instrument needed for his scientific studies. His library of books, charts, manuscripts and maps was more valuable then anything else in his possession at the time of his death.
Stauffer was married three times. He evidently married for the first time during his stay in Philadelphia. By 1850 he was married to Sarah L. Stauffer, his third wife; she died in 1875. He had five children, including one adopted daughter. One of his sons was the engineer and engraver David McNeely Stauffer. Another son was the newspaper publisher and poet Henry Francis Stauffer.
Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Cope, E. D., (Edward Drinker), 1840-1897; Cresson, Ezra Townsend; Darlington, William, 1782-1863; Durand, Elie M.; Farlow, W. G., (William Gilson), 1844-1919; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880; Hanson, Hugh C.; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Houghton, J. S.; Le Conte, John L. (John Lawrence), 1825-1883; Lesquereux, Leo, 1806-1889; Morris, John G., (John Gottlieb), 1803-1895; Porter, Thomas Conrad, 1822-1901; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891; Riley, Charles V., (Charles Valentine), 1843-1895; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881; Smithsonian Institution.; Botany.; Learned institutions and societies.; Natural history.; Paleontology.; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Scientists.; Zoology.
- Correspondence
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Dec. 21, 1844; 10x8; Atlee, Washington L. (Washington Lemuel), 1808-1878
    Scope and Contents note
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 1p.and add., end. Mutilated. Business.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, Oct. 15, 1850; 10x8; Morris, John G., (John Gottlieb), 1803-1895
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Mutilated. Concerning botany.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Mt. Joy, June 18, 1851; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. Mutilated. Concerning botany.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, Aug. 19, 1851; 10x8; Morris, John G., (John Gottlieb), 1803-1895
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Sept. 29, 1851; 10x8; Barnes, Albert, 1798-1870
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p., end. Mutilated. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Aug. 9, 1852; 10x8; Beck, John
    A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Refuses request.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, March 6, 1853; 10x8; Lesquereux, Leo, 1806-1889
    Columbia, A.L.S. 4p.,end. Mutilated. Concerning botany, paleontology and reptiles.
    General note
    Not located 4/2010.
  - Letter to [Jacob Stauffer], April 14, 1853; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Lesquereux, Leo, 1806-1889
    Columbia, A.L.S. 4p. Mutilated. Concerning insects and natural history.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Lancaster, July 11, 1853; 10-1/2x8; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Mutilated. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, July 26, 1853; 10x8; James, Thomas Potts, 1803-1882
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.,end. Mutilated. Concerning mosses. Refers to Gray.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Sept. 5, 1853; 10x8; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Mutilated. Concerning botany.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer,Mt. Joy, Sept. 26, 1853; 8x5; Darlington, William, 1782-1863
    West Chester, A.L.S. 3p.and end. Friendly letter. Botany.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Jan. 4, 1855; 8x5; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    A.L.S. 2p., end. Mutilated. Business.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Jan. 20, 1855; 8x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    A.L.S. 4p. Mutilated. Concerning snakes. Refers to the natural history of Pennsylvania. Refers to Haldeman.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Feb. 15, 1855; 8-1/2x5; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    A.L.S. 2p., end. Concerning snakes and salamanders.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Feb. 16, 1855; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Durand, Elias, 1794-1873
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and add.,end. Mutilated. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, May 20, 1855; 8x4-1/2; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 5p. and end. Concerning entomology. Refers to Say and the academy of natural sciences.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, May 27, 1855; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning entomology.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, June 4, 1855; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Concerning entomology. Refers to Haldeman.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, June 22, 1855; 7x4-1/2; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, A.P.S. 1p. and end. Concerning entomology.
  - Letter to [Jacop] Stauffer, June 25, 1855; 12x7-1/2; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Concerning insects.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, July 10, 1855; 8x5; Florist, Ed
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Would like articles on botany.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, July 15, 1855; 6-1/2x3-1/2; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 3p. and end. Concerning entomology.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Sept. 17, 1855; 10x7-1/2; James, Thomas Potts, 1803-1882
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p., end. Mutilated. Friendly letter. Concerning a drugstore Stauffer is considering buying.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, Sept. 22, 1855; 6-1/2x4; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning entomology. Refers to Guex and the Academy of Natural Sciences.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Nov. 6, 1855; 7x4-1/2; Darlington, William, 1782-1863
    West Chester, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Botany.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Dec. 26, 1855; 8x5; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Concerning insects. Refers to Haldeman.
  - Letter to [Jacob Stauffer], March 22, 1856; 6x4; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning birds, entomology and Rathvon.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, May 8, 1856; 10x7-1/2; Hanson, Hugh C.
    A.L.S. 1p.and end. Mutilated. Concerning botanical work.
  - Letter to [Jacob Stauffer], June 18, 1856; 8x5; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Concerning entomology. He and his father take pleasure in Stauffer's articles.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, June 27, 1856; 12-1/2x8; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 2p.,end. Mutilated. Concerning entomology and Le Conte. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, June 28, 1856; 6x8; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Concerning insects. Refers to the academy of natural sciences.
  - Letter to [Jacob Stauffer], June 29, 1856; 10-1/2x8; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Mutilated. Concerning entomology and geology.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, July 9, 1856; 10-1/2x8; Haldeman, Samuel Stehman, 1812-1880
    Columbia, A.L.S. 2p. and add.,end. Mutilated. Concerning entomology and fowls.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, Oct. 12, 1856; 8x5; Hare, Robert, 1781-1858
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p. and end. Mutilated. Friendly letter. Refers to Henry.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Nov. 10, 1856; 8-1/2x5; LeConte, John L., (John Lawrence), 1825-1883
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Concerning insects.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Nov. 22, 1856; 8x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer F[ullerton], 1823-1887.
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Dec. 19, 1856; 8x5; Hanson, Hugh C.
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p., end. Concerning botanical publications.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Dec. 22, 1856; 7-1/2x5; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
    Germantown, A.L.S. 1p. Mutilated. Business.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Jan. 5, 1857; 7x4-1/2; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
    Germantown, A.L.S. 2p. Business.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Jan. 9, 1857; 8x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Washington, A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Would appreciate small rodents.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Jan. 13, 1857; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Hanson, Hugh C.
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Mutilated. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Jan. 16, 1857; 10x7-1/2; Hanson, Hugh C.
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Mutilated. Concerning botanical work.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Jan. 28, 1857; 8x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning mice, reptiles and insects. Comliments Stauffer on his illustrations.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer; Mt. Joy, Feb. 7, 1857; 8x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. Mutilated. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer,Mt. Joy, March 19, 1857; 7x4-1/2; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
    Germantown, A.L.S. 1p. Business.
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, April 19, 1857; 5-1/2x8; Rathvon, S. S., (Simon Snyder), 1812-1891
    Lancaster, A.L.S. 2p.,end. Mutilated. Concerning entomology. Refers to Haldeman, LeConte, and the Academy of Natural Sciences.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, May 15, 1857; 8-1/2x7; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
    Germantown, A.L.S. 3p. and end. Botany.
  - Letter to Jacob Stauffer, June 27, 1857; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
    Germantown, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Mutilated. Business.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Mt. Joy, Oct. 18, 1857; 8-1/2x5-1/2; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887
    Washington, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Concerning insects.
  - Letter to J[acob] Stauffer, Oct. 29, 1857; 8x5; Smith, J. Jay, (John Jay), 1798-1881
  - Letter to [Jacob] Stauffer, Nov. 2, 1857; 8x5; Porter, Thomas Conrad, 1822-1901